All right, בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody.
We start today the a new פרק, perek, and this is a
the fourth פרק perek here, השולח, Hasholeach, and the next פרק perek
are going to get us into a range of ideas not having
to do with גט. get. The first one is about גט. get.
And but it's not just that it's like a digression, like we
just ended a פרק perek with a couple of digressions about, you
know, leaving something or someone and assuming that they're still alive and
that things are in the state that they were in. It's a
פרק perek that focuses as we'll see תיקון עולם, Tikkun Olam, things
that the rabbis did for the betterment of the world and we'll
try to exactly explain what's meant by that phrase.
And also the interesting thing in addition to just sort of seeing
this idea of תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam as a motivating certain rabbinic
legislation and also demonstrating as we'll see rabbinic power, how they can
sometimes use that to shape דאורייתא d'Oraita the laws, to shape or
even sometimes contravene דאורייתא d'Oraita the laws. It's also great because it
introduces us to core conceptual issues around some of these different topics.
Like in what like some of the, you know, core functioning basis
of that topic is. A classic one is going to be of
course פרוזבול pruzbul and how they managed to deal with, you know,
the the annulling of debts that occurs on שמיטה. shemita. So in
addition to seeing about פרוזבול, pruzbul, we're going to obviously have an
opportunity to explore the mechanics of the functioning of debts on the
שמיטה shemita year and so on. Cases about slaves, other types of
really like, you know, diverse and core topics. So let's start with
our משנה, Mishnah, top of
ל"ב. Lamed Bet. השולח גט לאשתו, Hasholeach get l'ishto, a man sends
a גט get to his wife. So we are still within the
context of שליחות shlichut introduced in the of delivery of sending a
גט get introduced in the first פרק. perek. והגיע בשליח, V'higia bashaliach,
and he approached the שליח. shaliach. He reached the שליח, shaliach, presumably
we'll see whether he was running after him or he bumped into
him. או ששלח אחריו שליח, O sheshalach acharav shaliach, or he sent
another שליח shaliach after him in order to go, you know, specifically
with a message. ואמר לו, V'amar lo, and he or the שליח
shaliach said to שליח shaliach number one, גט שנתתי לך בטל, Get
shenatati lecha batel, that גט get that I gave you, it is
annulled. I am implicitly I am annulling it.
הרי הוא בטל, Harei hu batel, that is annulled. Now that already
is a big חידוש. chiddush. When did we ever hear you could
annul a גט? get? What does that mean? Right? So what is
that exact mechanism there? You could annul the שליחות, shlichut, you're my
agent, you're I can now say you're no longer my agent. But
the emphasis here is somehow annulling the גט, get, changing the status
of this piece of paper. So let me just say at this
stage, you know, and obviously we'll develop this in the גמרא Gemara
and we'll see maybe if we have a chance some תוספות. Tosafot.
But you know, since there's been all of this emphasis until now
about לשמה, lishmah, right? That the סופר sofer has to write לשמה,
lishmah, there's the whole discussion does the סופר sofer have to be
my שליח, shaliach, you know, I the husband have to be the
one that is sort of supervising. Maybe it's more the signing of
it that has to be לשמה, lishmah, but something's got to be
לשמה lishmah and it's got to be done sort of not just
on their own but with my ציווי, tzivuy, you know, my directive
and under at least my aegis. So that is the question is
then to what degree do I retain a certain control over the
status of the גט. get. The way sometimes this is expressed in
the אחרונים acharonim literature is I can be מבטל mevatel the לשמה
lishmah of the גט. get. Now what does that mean? I mean
the לשמה lishmah is a fact, it was written with the wife
and me and our names in mind. But what it means is
that the גט get is an expression of my will, right? So
if you think about the גט get says הרי את מותרת לכל
אדם Harei at muteret lechol adam or behold I am sending you
forth you are הרי את מותרת לכל אדם. Harei at muteret lechol
adam. Think about if it was another שטר. shtar. It's interesting, could
you do this by another שטר? shtar? There's a שטר קידושין. shtar
kiddushin. הרי את מקודשת לי, Harei at mekudeshet li, that would be
the key of it. Or if there's a שטר מכר, shtar mecher,
שדי מכורה לך, Sadi mechurah lach, שדי נתונה לך. Sadi netunah lach.
It's a written expression of my will. If I actually go ahead
and not just casually change my mind, but actually verbally articulate that
my will is changed and this no longer expresses my will then
does it stop being a verbal expression of my will and just
a piece of paper?
Okay, it can't be קידושין, kiddushin, I mean you've got to go
through גירושין. geirushin.
What? No no no but before it's given, before it act, before
it's happened, before it's operated. Okay, it's not needed to sustain the
status but it's needed to effect the status. All right, so that's
the so that seems to be the logical conception and that's why
when the אחרונים acharonim talk about being מבטל mevatel the לשמה lishmah
they just mean because all of this big deal about my supervision
and directive and לשמה lishmah that like was a real issue by
גט. get. We could talk about whether it also exists how much
it could exist if I were to write a שטר קידושין. shtar
kiddushin. Okay but it doesn't exist for example when I write שדי
נתונה לך, Sadi netunah lach, okay
so you know it doesn't need לשמה, lishmah, right? You could have
pre-filled that out the סופר, sofer, you know, the only reason they're
not supposed to pre-fill it for the גמרא Gemara is because of
a גזירה gezeirah of גיטין, Gittin, right? So that is less about
that sustain, you know, about that focus. So let's start with our
משנה, Mishnah, top of ל"ב. Lamed Bet. demand that it be a
full expression of my will. But the גט get is that, and
therefore there seems to be this ability that if I verbally, now
you could say why is verbal enough? Maybe you would need an
actual written thing to revoke it, okay, but there's that assumption that
or the משנה Mishnah assumes that no, if I can verbally annul
the גט get and that it stops sort of being a גט.
get. It stops being that expression of my will, okay. But what
we're going to see, how that mechanics works. Now what I just
explained to you is פשט pshat of the משנה, Mishnah, we will
see at the bottom of today's דף, daf, at the bottom of
the עמוד ב, Amud Beis, that there are some that disagree and
that actually read that all you're really doing here, some in the
גמרא, Gemara, is annulling the שליחות, shlichus, is saying you're no longer
my agent, but that's not the language of the משנה Mishnah at
all. Okay, so he sends after and he catches up with the
שליח shaliach or he sends another שליח shaliach after him and says
that גט get is annulled, הרי הוא בטל, harei hu batel, the
גט get is annulled. קדם אצלו אשתו, Kadam etzlo ishto, או ששלח
אצלה שליח, o sheshalach etzlah shaliach, ואמר לה, ve'amar lah, גט ששלחתי
לך בטל, get sheshalachti lach batel, he runs ahead, beats the שליח
shaliach and gets to and gets to his wife, or he sends
a שליח shaliach number two to his wife and says that גט
get that I have sent you, that you have not yet received,
right? Once the גט get takes effect, it's over. But that גט
get that I sent you is annulled, before you've received it, הרי
זה בטל, harei zeh batel, that annuls it. אם משהגיע גט לידה,
Im meshehigia get leyadah, here you go Michael, once the גט get
is handed over, שוב אינו יכול לבטלו, shuv eino yachol levatlo, obviously
then you could what, you could burn the גט, get, she's already
divorced, so annulling it doesn't mean anything. Okay, one minute. בראשונה היה
עושה בית דין, Barishonah hayah oseh beis din, now what this does
requires now is that if you're going to annul the גט, get,
you have to do it in a way where the where the
where the relevant parties know immediately. So you either tell the שליח
shaliach and therefore the שליח shaliach won't deliver it or you tell
the woman. Okay,
בראשונה, Barishonah, originally you were allowed to annul the גט get and
nobody would know, not nobody, but the immediately relevant parties would not
know. בראשונה היה עושה בית דין במקום אחר, Barishonah hayah oseh beis
din bemakom acher, you could convene a בית דין beis din back
in your hometown while the שליח shaliach is on the plane carrying
the גט get to your wife,
ומבטלו umevatlo and you could annul it in front of your בית
דין. beis din. התקין רבן גמליאל הזקן, Hitkin Rabban Gamliel HaZaken, now
I think you could imagine why that's a bit of a problem.
התקין רבן גמליאל הזקן שלא יהו עושין כן מפני תיקון עולם, Hitkin
Rabban Gamliel HaZaken shelo yehu osin ken mipnei tikkun olam, for the
sake of the betterment of the world,
he established that you are not allowed to do that because obviously
you'll do that, the שליח shaliach thinks it's still good, the woman
thinks it's still good, everybody where the שליח shaliach is going in
Atlanta thinks it's good, okay, and you in your little village somewhere
in Bialystok or whatever, you and your little בית דין beis din
know that it's no good. Obviously that's a disaster, right? So therefore
they said you're not allowed to do what, and ah, so the
question is let's say you ignored the בית דין'ס beis din's תקנה
takkanah and you went ahead and did it. So that will be
the גמרא'ס Gemara's question: בטל או אינו מבוטל. batel o eino mevutal.
Okay, the other yes, but anyway, but there you have the mechanics
that you're allowed to annul and the question and the תקנה takkanah
that it has to be to the relevant
parties.
Yes, Dov. Where we learn it from?
Where we learn it from? וכתב לה. Vechatav lah.
So דאורייתא, de'oraisa, yeah.
But the idea that that means not just
describing a particular act of writing, but somehow defining it in a
more intense way as the ongoing expression of the husband's will, right?
Probably is
if there's a validity to his will in the first place and
it's kind of transferred to the document.
right,
I'm
trying to think of some kind of parallel in some other...
but what bothers you, that he's allowed to annul it before his
will's been effective?
Yeah, not that he's allowed to, but
that like if the document was valid and was in the proper
way
and then it should... I don't understand the mechanism by which it
should stay valid. How about stopping
a check before before it's been cashed? You like
that. Oh good, okay. Yes.
Is there some formula that he has to say? הרי זה בטל?
Harei zeh batel? Meaning what other words could work? Or yes, I
mean the
גמרא'ס Gemara's going to look...
no, he doesn't have to repeat it.
ששלחתי לך בטל. Sheshalachti lach batel.
Oh,
הרי זה בטל. Harei zeh batel. Okay. No, הרי זה בטל Harei
zeh batel is the משנה Mishnah speaking. If he says "that גט
get is בטל," batel, quote unquote,
then the משנה Mishnah says "behold it works, that's effective." Okay.
All right, let's look at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. The difference with
with the check is is I imagine you could un-stop the check
before it got cashed and then it would go back to being
valid, right? So we'll have to sort of see about that. I
assume that's true, right? Yes? Does anybody know, is that true? Can
you un-stop a stop check? I assume if you stop and un-stop
it and it hasn't been presented yet... what? It depends on the
bank. Oh, okay, fine.
If you issued a check... I see. We don't see רבן גמליאל
הזקן Rabban Gamliel HaZaken in the ש"ס Shas very often.
Yeah, I know. So he's pretty early, and here he is. I
see. We don't see רבן גמליאל הזקן Rabban Gamliel Hazaken in the
משנה Mishna usually. Yeah, I know. So he's pretty early and here
he's a central figure. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
הגיעו לא קתני Higu lo katani אלא הגיע. ela higia. It doesn't
say you sent the... you know, after you sent him you caught
up with him. It just says you caught up, which sort of
means like you bumped into him, this is the way the גמרא
Gemara reads it. 'Caught up with him' means you're right with him,
but it just says you sent a שליח shaliach and then you
caught up. Okay, what... you know, if you caught up with him,
it has a sense that you were focused on getting to him
and you caught up with him. It just says הגיע, higia, you
happen to run... bump into him, אפילו ממילא, afielu mimaila, even if
it was unintended. ולא אמרינן לצורא דאחמכמנא, velo amrinan letzura d'achamchaman, and
we don't say like oh, you bump into him and you're at
the bar and you say, 'Oh, you're still here? You know what?
It's בטל.' batel. Okay, so if you're... maybe I should say that
if you're not intentional, it's not clear you're focused on annulling the
get, and it seems more a little bit of a whim, then
maybe that should not be a good ביטול. bitul. And maybe the
only reason you're doing it is because you just figure like it's
an opportunity to give your wife a hard time. So therefore maybe
I should say that that ביטול bitul is not good, or at
least I should be concerned that the ביטול bitul is not word,
and that would actually put the woman in the worst situation, she'd
be in like that... you know, in that limbo. Anyway, so we
don't say that. Now moving on, או ששלח אחריו שליח, o sheshalach
acharyu shaliach, or scenario number two is you sent שליח shaliach number
two after שליח shaliach number one. למה לי, lama li, why do
I need to say that? You already told me you can annul
it.
So מהו דתימא, mahu detaima, I might have thought לא אלימא שליחותא
דבתרא משליחותא דקמא דליבטליה, lo alima shlichuta d'batra mishlichuta d'kama d'livatlei,
שליחות shlichus number two is not stronger than שליחות shlichus number one
that it could override it. קמשמע לן kamashmalan that it is. Okay,
so meaning you know why don't we say, 'Look, שליח shaliach number
one', I mean if you want to think about it this way,
right? The גמרא Gemara before spoke about the... about מילי לא מימסרן
לשליח, milei lo mimsaru l'shaliach, you know about the power of having
your שליחות shlichus represented in the physical object of the get. שליח
shaliach number one has the שליחות, shlichus, has the physical object of
the get. You're coming with words to try to override the status
of the get. If the husband himself were present and saying that,
you know, that actually... you know, that obviously would be more powerful.
But here, maybe your role as a שליח, shaliach, you don't enough
embody the husband. You know, your role is not powerful enough to
annul my role or my status as a שליח shaliach or the
status of the get. You know,
because I obviously here am playing more of the representative of the
husband. So maybe just the mechanics wouldn't work. That's actually an interesting
thing to think about that. You know, in this scenario also makes
me think about like the whole... you'll find this as a bizarre
comparison, but anyway, the whole עקידת יצחק akeidat Yitzchak story. You know,
because God first says like, you know, to אברהם Avraham like, you
know, 'Go bring him as an עולה.' olah. And then he sends
a שליח shaliach to annul it, right? Then the angel says, אל
תשלח ידך אל הנער... אל תעש לו מאומה. al tishlach yadcha el
hana'ar... al taas lo me'uma. So the thing is like אברהם Avraham
could have said like, 'You know, if I say... I don't trust
the שליח, shaliach, God, if you want to annul it you'll have
to do it yourself.' You know, so there אברהם Avraham was willing
to listen to שליח shaliach number two. Anyway, but here I could
think שליח shaliach number two doesn't have standing you know, or weight
against שליח shaliach number one. קמשמע לן kamashmalan that he does. Now,
that's the... case number two in the משנה. Mishna. How about the
next case? קדם הוא אצל אשתו, kadam hu etzel ishto, let's say
he caught up with his wife. למה לי, lama li, that should
be, I mean, more obvious. Now again, maybe not. Maybe you have
to focus your ביטול bitul on the guy holding the get, right?
Maybe telling it to your wife, right, is not the same act.
But anyway, למה לי, lama li, why? No, מהו דתימא, mahu detaima,
I might have thought כי היכי דאמרינן לצורא דאחמכמנא, ki haychi d'amrinan
letzura d'achamchaman, when do we say that we're not going to be
concerned that he's not serious and he's only doing this to cause
her anguish? הני מילי לשליח, hani mili l'shaliach, that's if he's talking
to the שליח shaliach where he doesn't have the opportunity to play
with her emotions directly. But לדידה, l'didah, he's going to her and
she's been waiting and waiting for the get and finally he sent
it and then he comes to her and he says something and
that... I mean you could... that's like really tragic. And you could
really understand how he could be like creating her enormous anguish by
that. ודאי לצורא דאחמכמנא, vadavai letzura d'achamchaman, let's really be concerned that
he's just doing it to cause her anguish and maybe he's not
serious. So and the חידוש chiddush is we don't say that.
קמשמע לן kamashmalan that we don't say that. Oh, now case number
four, ששלח אצלה שליח, sheshalach etzlah shaliach,
he sent a שליח shaliach to her. What's the חידוש chiddush about
that? למה לי, lama li, what's the... what's the חידוש chiddush about
that? No, מהו דתימא, mahu detaima, I might have thought איהו דלא
טרח אדעתיה לצורא. ihu d'lo tarach adaitei l'tzura. You know what? He
is not going to schlepp out and get on a plane and
fly to where she is just in order to, you know, just
anguish her. Okay, it's not worth his... his effort and his schlepp
of a שליח. shaliach. But to hire some guy to have some...
somebody else put out the effort and he can actually sit in
the comfort of his own home and cause his wife this anguish,
דלא איכפת ליה כי טרח, delo ichpas lei ki tarach, he doesn't
care if the שליח shaliach is exerting effort. So ודאי לצורא דאחמכמנא
vadavai letzura d'achamchaman and he's directly sending this message to his wife
and causing her anguish. So maybe that certainly he's only doing it
for that reason and that should be enough
to at least raise questions about the validity of the ביטול. bitul.
קמשמע לן kamashmalan that we don't say that. Okay, so that is
point number one going through the various scenarios of the משנה, Mishnah,
but anyway all those cases are cases that work. Now the last
line of the משנה Mishnah or before the תקנה. takana. אם שהגיע
גט לידו, Im shehigi'a get leyado, אין יכול לבטלו. ein yakol levatlo.
Once the get has been given over to her, he can't annul,
she's divorced, end of story. So the גמרא Gemara says, פשיטא, Pshita,
obviously she's divorced, she's divorced, he can't change it once that's been
effected. No, לא צריכה, lo tzericha, דמהדר לה מעיקרא לבטלויה. demahader la
me'ikara levatloye. So no, what we know, the point is, is that
we know that he was running after the שליח shaliach to try
to be מבטל mevatel it. Okay, right? Like
the שליח shaliach just gives a get to the wife and he,
you know, it's like one of those, he runs to him, did
I get it in time? I wanted to be מבטל. mevatel. He
says, oh sorry buddy, just happened two minutes ago. Okay, so in
that case, right, it's clear, you know, that what he wanted to
do. What?
Saved by the buzzer?
Exactly, exactly. It's like totally a made-for-movie scene. Okay, so in that
case, so מהו דתימא, mahu deteima, I might have thought איגלאי מילתא
למפרע דביטולי בטליה. iglaei milta lemafreia d'bitulei batlei. Ah, so this now
it's clear that that's what he's trying to do. Maybe this should
show us that he was מבטל mevatel it. Now it doesn't mean
like we have to be concerned that he was מבטל mevatel in
some hidden בית דין beis din because anyway, you know, the whatever,
then whatever we'd find out. So what it means is not that
he actually was מבטל, mevatel, but maybe we should be concerned that
since he's trying to do it and it's clear that's what he
wants to do, that that therefore effectively was a ביטול bitul already.
That, you know, expression of his desire. Okay, וקא משמע לן v'ka
mashma lan that we're not concerned about that. Now that's a little
funny because it raises a couple of questions. Right? One is since,
you know, the non-verbal act, does that count as a verbal act?
We normally say דברים שבלב אינם דברים. devarim shebelev einam devarim. You
don't say any, if you don't articulate it, it doesn't have any
weight. So maybe that's the point of it. Okay, but number two
also is even if it was like he said it, right, if
he's not communicating it to the שליח, shaliach, right? So fine, it's
clear now that when you were running out, you know, through the
marketplace to get to us, right, you were trying to be מבטל
mevatel and it's like you were saying you're מבטל. mevatel. But you
weren't saying it to me, the שליח, shaliach, you weren't saying it
to the woman, you weren't saying it in front of a בית
דין, beis din, right? So even if your
attempt can in hindsight, and that's another question, will we reinterpret a
non-verbal attempt in hindsight? be seen as that type of an expression?
But it wasn't being said to the right parties. Okay, so maybe
that's why the גמרא Gemara says קא משמע לן ka mashma lan
we're not concerned about it. Okay, but the obvious weakness about this,
I'll take the question then I'll tell you what תוספות Tosafos says.
The obvious problem that it wouldn't work is not because we doubt
that you really were trying to do it, but that trying is
not succeeding and you'd need to do the formal act, you know,
the act of speech in front of the right parties. Jenny, you
had a question?
Well, I was going to say it makes sense because the whole
משנה Mishnah so far is setting up this idea that he's changing
his mind and going and saying it's that's like problematic so we
need to know how far you can carry it, so like you're
מבטלing mevatel it in your head before it's been given, maybe totally
maybe that would work according to some?
Right, exactly, the very fact that a speech act can change the
status of a get, right, you know, or even if it just
changes the status of the שליחות, shlichus, right, you obviously need to
formalize that act or everything is up for grabs, right? Which is
exactly correct. So yeah, clarify exactly what's confusing? Exactly,
what exactly constitutes right that act that an. Dov, did you have
a question? No? Okay.
In the משנה Mishnah it seems that, you know, you have to
have actually successfully reached that שליח shaliach or the woman or whatever
it is, meaning even if you're running through the marketplace saying I
want this שליחות shlichus to be בטל, batel, if the guy is
like, you know, like a block ahead and doesn't hear you.
Right, that's what I said. There's a couple of problems. A, we
only find out in hindsight. B, you never said anything and דברים
שבלב אינם דברים. devarim shebelev einam devarim. And C, even if it
was as if you said something, right, you didn't say it to
the, like I said, you didn't say it to the right parties.
Exactly, yes.
This is kind of the case we had recently where the guy
didn't quite make it back in thirty days, right, and
he was shouting from the other side of the river. He's not.
Right. Right. Okay, so let's take a look at תוספות Tosafos what?
The graduate?
Oh right, right, right, right.
Yeah, that's exactly what I said, it's a made-for-movie scene. So take
a look at תוספות Tosafos here about ten lines from before the
lines get wide. It starts with the word דלאו כלום הוא. delav
klum hu. קא משמע לן מתניתין דלאו כלום הוא. ka mashma lan
matnitin delav klum hu. וטעמא, v'ta'ama, the reason says תוספות, Tosafos, משום
דבאותה שעה שהוא רץ, mishum d'be'ota sha'ah she'hu ratz, לא נודע דעתו,
lo noda da'ato,
his intent was not known, לא לשליח ולא לאשה, lo lashaliach v'lo
l'isha, not to the relevant parties. Okay, so if you haven't communicated
that intent to the relevant parties at the time, it's not good.
לא לשליח ולא לאשה ולא לבית דין. lo lashaliach v'lo l'isha v'lo
l'beis din. Okay, והוו להו דברים שבלב, v'havu lehu devarim shebelev,
and it was things that were unarticulated, שאינם דברים, she'einam devarim, they
don't count, אף על פי שנאמן לומר כך היה בלבי, af al
pi sheneman lomar kach haya belibi, even if we trust you that
you were trying to do it, it doesn't matter. You didn't communicate
it to the right parties. Okay. ואף על גב דבעלמא גבי ההוא
דזבין אדעתא למיסק לארץ ישראל. v'af al gav d'be'alma gabei hahu d'zavin
ada'ata lemisak l'eretz yisrael. כיוון דלא חשש לפרש רוצה שיתקיים הדבר בכל
ענין אבל כאן עושה כל מה שיכול לעשות. keivan d'lo chashash lefaresh
rotze sheyitkayeim hadavar bechol inyan aval kan oseh kol mah sheyachol la'asos.
So let's just pause for a second. תוספות Tosfos basically says why
is it דברים שבלב אינם דברים, devarim shebelev einam devarim, that unarticulated
thoughts don't count? So the obvious answer is not what תוספות Tosfos
says, תוספות Tosfos will sort of say the obvious answer in a
minute, but the obvious answer is because you can't run a legal
system where people were saying this is what I was thinking, right?
If it doesn't become articulated and explicit and measurable and whatever, knowable,
it just doesn't have weight. תוספות, Tosfos, however, says that no, the
reason is, at least in some cases, the reason is because since
you didn't bother to actually say it, you couldn't have really been
that committed to that thought, okay? If you really wanted that thought
to be relevant to the transaction, you would have articulated it. So
תוספות Tosfos says well if that's the reason, that doesn't work here
because here the שליח shaliach he's trying to say it, he's running,
and not the שליח shaliach the בעל, ba'al, running and running and
running, he just didn't get up to the שליח shaliach yet. So
you can't say he wasn't really serious, of course he was serious,
right? He was serious. Okay, so תוספות Tosfos says so maybe it
should be דברים devarim and it should be like he said it.
Of course the point against it still is, okay, let it be
like he said it, he didn't say it to the שליח, shaliach,
right? That's still the problem. He didn't say it to the שליח
shaliach at the right time. Okay, so מכל מקום, mikol makom, תוספות,
Tosfos, his first answer is עשאום כדברים שבלב. asa'um k'devarim shebelev.
No, nevertheless, yeah you're right, you know, maybe this really should work,
maybe it should be like he did say it, and maybe now
in hindsight we should and maybe if the שליח shaliach saw him,
because תוספות Tosfos earlier described it that the שליח shaliach saw him
running after him. If the שליח shaliach saw that he was running
after him, but he thought the husband was running after him because
he was saying like hurry up and do it already, the שליח
shaliach didn't understand what that meant. So תוספות Tosfos sets up a
scenario, the שליח shaliach saw the husband running after him, at the
time he thought the husband was urging him on, in hindsight the
שליח shaliach now the husband says I was trying to be מבטל,
mevatel, everybody believes the husband, in hindsight the שליח shaliach looks back
at you know in his memory about what happened and realizes that's
what the husband was trying to do. And if we say דברים
שבלב הוי דברים, devarim shebelev havei devarim, why don't we interpret
retroactively that the שליח shaliach heard the husband's ביטול? bitul? Okay, that
would be the question. I mean one could imagine an interesting case,
let's say I'm the husband and I say to the שליח, shaliach,
okay, Dov's my שליח, shaliach, I say I am מבטל mevatel the
גט, get, and Michael and Charlie here heard me, but Dov was
distracted or I wasn't articulating it well and Dov heard it say
I'm thrilled about the גט, get, I don't know what Dov heard,
right? Presumably in
retroactively once we clarify that, no, wouldn't that be a good ביטול
bitul or not? I said it to him, whatever, he just didn't
realize it at the time, okay? So תוספות Tosfos says what about
this case? You ran after him, at the time he interpreted it
one way, he remembered afterwards, he looked back at it retroactively after
you clarify your thoughts, he thought about it another way, does that
retroactively become as if you actually did say it? So that's the
type of thing that תוספות Tosfos is playing with. In this stage
תוספות Tosfos thinks well maybe it should be. So then why didn't
the ביטול bitul work? So what I really wanted you to see
this punchline, again and again I think we could have disagreed with
תוספות Tosfos at like three different points here to say that it
shouldn't work, but תוספות Tosfos thinks maybe it really should have worked,
okay? And then he says, but nevertheless, he says that the rabbis
said it won't work because obviously ואין להקשות וכי איכא מידי דמדאורייתא
לא הוי גט ומדרבנן הוי גט, v'ein l'hakshos v'chi ika midi d'mid'Oraisa
lo havei get u'miderabbanan havei get, that how could this be if
that really should work as a ביטול bitul that the rabbis are
stopping it from working, okay? תוספות Tosfos says
שכיון דקצת דמי לדברים שבלב לא חשיב אקימת דבור מן התורה. shekeivan
d'ktzas dami l'devarim shebelev lo chashiv akimas dibur min haTorah. Okay, it's
basically the rabbis are going to annul it but it won't look
so bad. So the point I really wanted to introduce to you
here, and it was a little complicated, sorry if I lost you,
but anyway, was that תוספות Tosfos is already introducing an idea that's
going to come up pretty soon in the גמרא, Gemara, which is
that the rabbis sometimes can use their power to override and contravene
a דאורייתא. d'Oraisa. So תוספות Tosfos imagines that there could be cases
here where actually it was a good ביטול bitul and we're going
to prevent it from working. Okay, and as long as it doesn't
look like we're so blatantly contravening a דאורייתא. d'Oraisa. All right, so
anyway, but that's a little bit maybe jumping ahead of ourselves. Bottom
line is this does not work because of דברים שבלב, devarim shebelev,
which gives תוספות Tosfos an interesting opportunity to explore why is דברים
שבלב אינם דברים, devarim shebelev einam devarim, even if it wasn't דברים
שבלב, devarim shebelev, was it communicated to the right person, did the
שליח shaliach see him running after him or not see him running
after him, even if he did, if he only realized what it
meant in hindsight, bottom line is it's דברים שבלב, devarim shebelev, you
know, you're not clear at the time, you're not saying anything at
the time, it's דברים שבלב. devarim shebelev. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara
continues, yes?
Quick question, would this be for any type of שטר shtar if
you
were sending it through a שליח? shaliach? So that's what I said,
that's not well, if you're being מבטל mevatel the שליחות shlichus maybe,
but if you're being מבטל mevatel the status of the גט get
maybe the גט get is unique. So that's not so clear. תנו
רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, let's take a look at now you know David
asked about what is there a formula, so this ברייתא's braisa going
to discuss what formula there might be to do the ביטול. bitul.
תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: בטל הוא, batel hu, if you say it
is בטל, batel, אי אפשי בו, ee efshi bo, I do not
desire it, דבריו קיימים, devarav kayamim, then it's good. So the interesting
thing is I no longer want it is enough to be מבטל
mevatel even though you're not actually doing an act of, you know,
nullifying it per se, not negating its status, I'm just saying it
no longer ex expresses my desire, right? אי אפשי בו, ee efshi
bo, that works, and the גט get is בטל. batel. Okay. פסול
הוא, pasul hu, if you say it's invalid, אינו גט, eino get,
it's not a good גט, get, לא אמר כלום, lo amar klum,
you didn't say anything because that is not seen as an act
of annulling or expressing that it is no longer your will, it
is just your statement of incorrect fact. You're saying it's פסול. pasul.
Really? Where's the פסול? psul? Right? You're saying it's not valid. Really?
Why is it not valid? Okay, so if you're not making a
declarative statement of withdrawing your, you know, your will or a declarative
statement of voiding it. All right, of course that gets very like
a, you know, very razor edge, like when are you saying one
thing, when are you saying the other, which is what the גמרא
Gemara is going to try to determine. Okay, so what?
ללמוד נדרים lilmod Nedarim again, exactly. Okay, okay, למימרא le-meimra to say
דבטל לישנא דליבטל משמע, de-batel lishna de-livatel mashma, to say when you
say it is בטל, batel, that means it should be בטל, batel,
right? I mean think about the act of קידושין. Kiddushin. הרי את
מקודשת לי. harei at mekudeshet li. Okay,
is that a description of fact or a description of behold I
am consecrating, you know, or betrothing you to me? Obviously it's the
B, but why isn't it A? Behold I'm just describing a reality.
You are מקודשת mekudeshet to me, right? You're my wife. Okay, so
anyway, but so in certain contexts language describes something as behold I,
you know, I am making this, I am effecting this reality. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says it sounds like בטל הוא batel hu
means it shall become בטל. batel. I am, I am being מבטל
mevatel it, okay, not that you're just describing its current status as
בטל. batel. והאמר רבה בר אבא אמר רב ששת ואמרי לה אמר
רבה בר אבוה
מקבולי מתנה שאמר ve-ha-amar Rabba bar Abba amar Rav Sheshet ve-amrei lah
amar Rabba bar Avuh me-kaboley matana she-amar דבטל, de-batel, don't we take
if somebody receives a מתנה matana and says לאחר שבאה מתנה לידו,
le-achar she-ba'ah matana le-yado, after he received the gift, מתנה זו מבוטלת,
matana zo mevu-telet, as this מתנה matana that I have received should
be annulled, okay, תיבטל, ti-batel, this is clearly language of shall be,
shall be annulled, אי אפשי בה, ee efshi bah, I do not
desire it, לא אמר כלום, lo amar klum, you didn't say anything.
You already received the gift, right? If you didn't want to get
it, now go ahead and turn back and give it as a,
you know, give it as a donation somewhere, okay? But, but what?
Re-gift it, right. But you cannot annul it once you've received it,
okay? And you're saying I, I do not desire it, it should
be בטל, batel, it's too late. Okay. בטילה היא, beteila hi, it
is בטל, batel, אינה מתנה, eina matana, it is not a gift,
דבריו קיימין, devarav kayamin, that's good because that sounds like you're describing
the current status and here it's like the flip of the גט.
get. What you're saying is if you're saying it's not a gift,
that means I never received it as a gift. I never intended
to receive it as a gift. Not that I'm annulling its status
right now, but it was never a gift. I never, that was
never my intent. Okay, so that's a little tricky even right there.
We're not going to over-worry about that, but we're going to focus
on the language. אלמא בטל מעיקרא משמע. alma batel me-ikara mashma.
So you see when it says it is בטל, batel, that means
you're saying it, it was never valid. You're not saying I am
annulling it, because if you said I am annulling it, it wouldn't
work by the gift. So if it's working by the gift, what
you're saying is it was never a valid gift. So what is
בטל batel telling? Is it describing the past or describing the future?
Are you saying it was never valid or are you saying I
am being מבטל mevatel it? So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, so אביי
Abaye says, בטל
שתי לשונות משמע. batel shtei leshonot mashma. בטל batel can go either
way, right? Like I said, a lot of those statements הרי
את מקודשת, harei at mekudeshet, הרי זה בטל, harei zeh batel, are
you describing a status that exists or a status that you are
effecting? So אביי Abaye says it could go either way. So משמע
דבטל, mashma de-batel, it's, it sounds like it's already annulled, ומשמע דליבטל,
u-mashma de-livatel, it shall become annulled through this act of speech. לגבי
גט לישנא דבהני ביה קאמר, le-gabey get lishna de-bahani beh ka-amar, and
it's clear when you're saying this, you're trying to affect the status
of what's going on, right? So by the גט, get, it's clear
what you're trying to do is to annul it. So we interpret
it in that context and we say it means it shall be
annulled, okay? דגבי מתנה לישנא דבהני ביה קאמר, de-gabey matana lishna de-bahani
beh ka-amar, and by מתנה, matana,
it's clear that you're trying to annul the מתנה. matana. The only
way that would work in the case of מתנה matana is to,
you know, is what do you call it, is if it refers
to the current status, not a status that you're trying to effect.
So we interpret it in accordance to what clearly is what you're
trying to accomplish. Okay, so you could explain this in one of
two ways. You could say, you know, words are ambiguous. I mean,
whatever, often statements are ambiguous and context, you know, makes it clear
what you're talking about. You know, like Dov said, that's the whole
discussion of ידיים שאינן מוכיחות, yadayim she-einan mokhichot, ידיים מוכיחות, yadayim mokhichot,
the context explains it. So since it's clear what I'm trying to
do, I say an ambiguous statement, so that'll clarify which one of
those versions I mean, right? So, so, you know, under the חופה,
chuppah, הרי את מקודשת לי harei at mekudeshet li clearly means one
thing, right? You know, if I, you know, if somebody says to
his wife, "How could you cheat on me? But הרי את מקודשת
לי," harei at mekudeshet li, then he means something else, okay? So
it's describe, right, it's not describing what he's, anyway. So, so, so
words depend on their context. And here you're trying to effect something,
we assume that it means the way it does, you know, in
that context. That's like the simplest way to explain
this. The other way to explain it is
that it's a legal point
that we will choose to interpret. We don't really know what you
said. But we have to decide halachically what it means. So we're
going to choose to interpret it right in the way which is
clearly most in accordance with what we imagine you were doing. But
there's no need to say something that complicated here. The simple sense
is the sentence is somewhat ambiguous,
okay, and therefore we use the context to explain it. So now
the
גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay. Okay. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, said אביי, Abaye, נקטינן, Naktinan, we
actually adopt the position that שליח מתנה הרי הוא כשליח הגט. shaliach
matana harei hu keshaliach haget. That here's now the question, you send
a guy with a writ to give a gift. That is the
same as a guy who's bringing a writ of divorce. Now given
the context you might think it means I could be מבטל mevatel
right the you know the שטר מתנה. shtar matana. But let's see
what
the גמרא Gemara says. נפקא מינה Nafka mina what this is teaching
me is להולך לאו כזכי דמי. leholech lav kizchi dami. You might
remember that סוגיא, sugiyah, it's a סוגיא sugiyah that keeps on repeating
it. If I said to the שליח, shaliach, הולך, holech, go deliver
this writ of gift
to Charlie there, I'm gifting him my house here and go deliver
it to him. So why don't we just say because I won
the Powerball so therefore I don't need my house anymore. So why
don't we say that as soon as I give it to the
שליח shaliach he doesn't have to give it to Charlie, right? It's
a זכות zechut for Charlie, it's a gift and he just takes
possession of it on Charlie's behalf, זכין לאדם שלא בפניו. zachin leadam
shelo befanav. So we say no because I said הולך, holech, deliver
it,
I am basically saying I am not prepared for Charlie to own
it until it gets delivered. Okay if so therefore הולך לאו כזכי.
holech lav kizchi. Yeah it works for him to represent Charlie but
my will I have not allowed that to happen okay so therefore
Charlie won't get it until the גט get until the שטר shtar
actually reaches him because I have not allowed him yet to own
it until that point. Now so that's certainly that's like a גט.
get. By גט get even if I said to the שליח shaliach
בי זכין be zochin this גט get for my wife it wouldn't
work because that is not seen as an objective benefit for the
woman and therefore it only works when it gets to her or
when it gets to her שליח shaliach that she appointed. Okay so
that's the comparison. That the same way a גט get does not
work until it gets to the other side, a שטר מתנה shtar
matana when I say הולך holech deliver it there might be other
languages which are different but if I use the language of הולך
holech it's not effective until it gets to the other side. Now
the question that's not explored here is okay that's all wonderful but
in this context now I want to know the next question so
if he's delivering this שטר מתנה shtar matana and it's not yet
effective can I now annul the שטר מתנה shtar matana before it
reaches him? Right? And that seems to be what אביי Abaye is
saying in this context. It's like a שטר הגט shtar haget meaning
A it's not yet effective and B you could annul it like
you could annul the גט. get. And that's I think a really
interesting question because it gets to the issue of how unique is
this idea of being
מבטל mevatel how is this unique to the גט. get. We talked
about the whole לשמה lishmah emphasis right so here's the question which
is not going to be explored in this גמרא. Gemara. Like it's
tantalizingly being held out right but it's not actually being explored. Is
this actually unique to גט get or not? Can I be מבטל
mevatel the שליח shaliach by a gift? But let's say I just
said I'm not מבטל mevatel you you're still my agent I'm just
saying that the that the שטר מתנה shtar matana is null and
void. Does that work or not? It sounds from this that it
does but the גמרא Gemara is not really spelling that out. Okay
so now the גמרא Gemara continues. רבינא Ravina אשכחיה לרב נחמן בר
יצחק. ashkechei leRav Nachman bar Yitzchak. רבינא Ravina found רב נחמן בר
יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak דתלי וקאי בעברא דדשא detalei vekaei beivara
dedasha he was sort of there leaning against the door וכמיבעיא ליה
vekama mibaei lei
and he was asked the following question: בטל מהו? batel mahu? Let's
say he didn't say הרי הוא בטל harei hu batel
he just said בטל. batel. Okay so what's the story? Or תוספות
Tosfot said now בטל batel isn't even a sentence
so רש"י Rashi says that what you said is what does רש"י
Rashi say בטל batel
no ולא אמר הוא velo amar hu yeah you just said בטל.
batel. Okay I guess yeah it wasn't a sentence. Okay בטל batel
you didn't say בטל הוא. batel hu. Okay what's the story?
מהו? mahu? תיקו! teiku! We don't know! We don't know if that
means you're saying it's already בטל, batel, you're it shall be בטל,
batel, we don't know which way to read that.
אמר רב ששת Amar Rav Sheshet ואמרי לה במתניתא תנא veamrei lei
bematnita tena רב ששת Rav Sheshet and some say we taught in
a ברייתא: Baraita: גט זה לא יועיל, get zeh lo yoil, this
גט get shall not work, לא יתיר, lo yattir, should not permit
her, should not make her permitted, לא יעזוב, lo yaaziv, should not
make her like sent away, לא ישלח, lo yishalach, shall not send
her away as those are some of the languages in the גט
get itself, לא יגורש, lo yigoresh, shall no longer be effective to
divorce her, יהא כחרס yehe kacheres shall be like a pottery, יהא
כחרס ye kacheres shall pottery, תהא כחרס tehe kacheres shall be like
pottery, דבריו קיימים devarav kayyamim all that is good, all that is
saying clear that what you're trying to do you're trying to say
I am annulling its efficacy, okay, I am so I am doing
an act that saying it shall no longer be efficacious. and I
am annulling it.
אינו מועיל. eino mo’il. Now let's see. It does not work. אינו
מתיר. eino matir. It does not divorce. It does not permit. אינו
מעזיב. eino ma’aziv. It does not again leave her. אינו משלח eino
meshaleach does not send her away. אינו מגרש eino megaresh does not
divorce. חרס הוא cheres hu it is pottery. כחרס הוא kecheres hu
it is like pottery, not it shall be like pottery, it is
like pottery. לא אמר כלום lo amar klum you did not say
anything. Okay, so again very subtle differences here between it shall be
X, I am doing an act and changing its status, or I
am just describing its current status. Okay, what do we say? Right,
present versus future or shall be. Right, what do we do if,
let's think about, what do we do about ביטול חמץ? bitul chametz?
Right,
יבטל ויהא yevatel veyehe right, ויהא veyehe it should be בטל batel
וליהוי veleheve and it should be like כעפרא דארעא ke'afra de'ara right,
it shall be, future oriented. Okay. Okay,
איבעיא להו, ibaia lehu, they have the following question: הרי הוא חרס
harei hu cheres behold it is cheres. Is that describing it or
is it saying I am making it this way? מאי הוא? mai
hu? What's the story? So אמר ליה רבינא לרב אחא בריה דרבא
ואמרי לה רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי, amar leh Ravina le-Rav
Acha brei de-Rava ve-amri lah Rav Acha brei de-Rava le-Rav Ashi, so
one said to the other, מאי שנא מהרי הוא הקדש, הרי הוא
הפקר. mai shena me-harei hu hekdesh, harei hu hefker. Behold it is
הקדש, hekdesh, behold it is הפקר, hefker, clearly you are effecting a
change of status, you mean it shall become, so why don't we
say הרי הוא חרס harei hu cheres is the same? All right.
So again, but it's a little different, the word חרס cheres is
a little different than הקדש hekdesh and הפקר hefker which clearly relates
to a speech act. You know, the way something becomes הקדש hekdesh
or הפקר hefker is through a speech act. When you say "behold
it is hekdesh," that context-free means I am making it hekdesh. Like
behold it is pottery, the word pottery does not in itself suggest
a speech act that changes something's status. Right? The same way the
word הקדש hekdesh does.
It changes from wood into pottery.
Oh that's also true. Right. Maybe it matters what it's made of.
It looked like a piece of wood, and I'm telling you it's
actually a piece of pottery. That's a good point. Anyway, so תוספות
Tosafot points out that, you know, this stuff, you can't fit this
stuff in a box. Like look at תוספות. Tosafot. מאי שנא מהרי
הוא הקדש. mai shena me-harei hu hekdesh. תוספות Tosafot says תימא, Teima,
דרישא ביין אינו מועיל משמע, de-reisha bein eino mo'il mashma, דכיכר זה
הקדש de-kikar zeh hekdesh שמועיל. she-mo'il. If you said this loaf of
bread is hekdesh, that would work.
בגט זה חרס be-get zeh cheres ודאי לא אמר כלום. vada'i lo
amar klum. It's certainly not good. So you can't just say, let's
look at the sentence structure, take out this word, put in that
word, and if it's the same sentence structure it'll still mean the
same thing, future or present. If a critical thing is by changing
that one word you've changed the context of the sentence. So it's
really hard to know like which way things fall out on this.
Okay. But anyway, תוספות Tosafot does not have an answer today. Now
the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay.
Now we get to the central conceptual question. חוזר ומגרש
בו או אינו חוזר ומגרש בו? chozer u-megaresh bo o eino chozer
u-megaresh bo? Okay. It's like I stopped my stop on my check.
Okay. I annulled it, and now I said, you know what, I
changed my mind again. Just give me the get, I'll give it
to her, after I said הרי הוא בטל. harei hu batel. Okay.
Have I actually effectively torn up the get? Okay, or not? I
now as you could ask that two ways: Can I reverse the
ביטול, bitul, right, or have I really, even when I said הרי
הוא בטל, harei hu batel, have I really changed the status of
the get or not? So let's take a look. חוזר ומגרש בו
או אינו חוזר ומגרש בו? chozer u-megaresh bo o eino chozer u-megaresh
bo? רב נחמן אמר חוזר ומגרש בו, Rav Nachman amar chozer u-megaresh
bo, you can reuse it. רב ששת אמר אינו חוזר ומגרש בו,
Rav Sheshet amar eino chozer u-megaresh bo, you cannot reuse it, you've
already destroyed it. והלכתא כוותיה דרב נחמן. vehilchata kevateih de-Rav Nachman. This
is like רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, that you can reuse it, which
is very shocking, right, because the whole language is all בטל, batel,
חרס, cheres, this, that, it shall not be מתיר, matir, it shall
not be, it's all focused on the efficacy of the get every
single word we've been reading right now, and he says, you know
what, you can actually reuse it. Now again, maybe you could say
you could remove your ביטול. bitul. Okay. It did annul the get
but you can remove that. But now let's see if how the
גמרא Gemara continues. It's also sometimes so disappointing, right, when you have
such a rich conceptual question and there's like no discussion. We're just
going to go to the end here. Okay. You have a page
and a half about הרי הוא בטל, harei hu batel, הרי הוא
חרס, harei hu cheres, הרי הוא whatever, and this is like one
sentence.
Anyway, okay. והלכתא כוותיה דרב נחמן. אמר ליה amar leh is this
true? וקיימא לן הלכתא כוותיה דרבי יוחנן ve-kayma lan hilchata kevateih de-Rabbi
Yochanan בחוזרת. be-chozeret. In a similar case we rule like רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan who says it goes back. What's the case? I say
to a woman, הרי את מקודשת לי בטבעת זו לאחר שלושים יום.
harei at mekudeshet li be-tabaat zu le-achar sheloshim yom. Here, Michael, go,
okay, take that. So I say this to Michelle over here. Anyway,
okay. And then, okay, and then what happens is,
can either side back out before the שלושים יום sheloshim yom arrives?
Okay. והדר ביה מהשתא. ve-hadar beih me-hashtah.
Well right. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says that you can. Okay.
Take a look at רש"י Rashi says דרבי יוחנן דאמר חוזרת. de-Rabbi
Yochanan de-amar chozeret. About 10 lines before it gets wide. בקידושין. be-Kiddushin.
בפרק האומר לחבירו. be-perek Ha-omer Le-chavero. אמר לאשה התקדשי לי במנה זה
לאחר שלושים יום וחזר בו בתוך שלושים יום. amar le-ishah hitkadshi li
be-maneh zeh le-achar sheloshim yom ve-chazar bo be-toch sheloshim yom. Okay. And
she- and she retracts.
some comparison? So we're going to see in a minute what's the
comparison. Anyway the גמרא Gemara says, look, before something was effective you
can, even though the act was done, the ring was given over,
right? Before it became effective, you can annul it and it's fully
annulled. So here too, you should be able to annul the Get.
Why can't you use it? Now it's a bizarre comparison, which is
what... so the גמרא Gemara says that. The גמרא Gemara says היכי
דמי? heichi dami? What... הכי השתא? hachi hashta? What type of comparison
is that? התם דיבור ודיבור הוא. hatam dibbur u'dibbur hu. There it's
all speech. אתי דיבור ומבטל דיבור. ati dibbur u'mevatel dibbur. Meaning, I'm
not being annulling some status of some object, I'm being annulling the
effect of the Kiddushin. Right? So that's like I'm not, so I'm
not changing the status of an object. There was something created through
speech can be annulled by speech. And I mean the way I
would conceptualize this is what you're just doing is that you're just
like preventing something from taking effect, okay? And that you can do
as long as it hasn't taken effect. הכא נהי דביטול לשליחותיה דשליח,
hacha nehi de'bitul li'shlichutei de'shaliach, here
when you said בטל, batel, yes it did something. What did it
do? It annulled the שליחות, shlichus, it annulled the agency. But גיטא
גופיה מי קא בטל? gita gufiah mi ka batel? Since when are
you annulling the Get itself? Okay, which basically what it means is
nobody ever denied your ability before something took effect to change its
status. You can annul an agency, you can stop a, postpone Kiddushin
from taking effect, okay? But whoever said that you have the ability
to change the legal status of a document? Okay, you don't want
it, rip it up. You don't want the שליח shaliach to deliver
it, be מבטל mevatel the שליח. shaliach. But this document is legitimate
and valid and how can your words change its legal status? Okay,
so that basically is the clear sense of this גמרא Gemara is...
everything we've been talking about until now that I gave a whole
nice little שיעור shiur on, you know, at the first משנה, mishna,
it's an expression of your will and therefore you can reverse your
will or whatever. So it says no, it's a legal document and
like if I wrote up a contract and it's sitting in my
safe, even if I, you know, say I no longer want it,
whatever, whatever, if at one stage I take it out and I
give it, of course it's still good. Right? When... how does it...
how does this affect the status of the document? Okay, now so
that's... now the problem with that explanation is that all of the
language here is directed to the status of the Get. So what
we'd have to say is, well we're going to reinterpret to be
מבטל mevatel the שליחות. shlichus. Okay, so it's like really very וכי
חריז
יהיה כי חריז יהיה כי חריז דשלוחא.
ve'chi
chariz
yi'heyeh chi chariz yi'heyeh chi chariz de'shlucha.
It's totally bizarre. So let's take a look at תוספות. Tosafot. Okay,
תוספות Tosafot says the following.
So he says like this:
התם דיבור ודיבור הוא. hatam dibbur u'dibbur hu. So here it's speech
and speech. מתוך הלשון משמע, mitoch ha'lashon mashma, the גמרא Gemara makes
it sound דאפילו ביטלו בפירוש אינו מבוטל. de'afilu bitlo be'perush eino mevutal.
Even if you explicitly said I want this to be 100% clear,
I am not מבטל mevatel the שליחות. shlichus. What I am doing
is, you see that piece of paper in your hand? That piece
of paper I am saying is now annulled. Okay? Even if you
actually were clearly explicit, it wouldn't work. Who cares? You can't
annul a Get. ודיבור לשליחות הוא דבטל. ve'dibbur li'shlichus hu de'batel. Right,
well I don't know, maybe we'll say you didn't annul the Get,
you annulled the שליחות shlichus no matter what you said. But the
point is fine. Okay? It sounds like this גמרא, Gemara, it's not
possible to annul the Get.
מדקאמר התם דיבור ודיבור הוא, mideka'amar hatam dibbur u'dibbur hu, משמע דהכא
לאו דיבור ודיבור הוא, mashma de'hacha lav dibbur u'dibbur hu, אלא דיבור
ומעשה. ela dibbur u'ma'aseh. It's words against something that an effect, something
that's been effected, that's real, that's concrete, and your words cannot change
the status of this concrete Get. וקאמר גיטא גופיה מי קא בטל,
ve'ka'amar gita gufiah mi ka batel, is the Get גופיה, gufiah, is
it really בטל? batel? משמע דאין לו כח לבטל. mashma de'ein lo
koach levatel. Is it
meaning... I'm not sure the words mean imply that, but תוספות Tosafot
says the words imply, is it... no, how could you be מבטל
mevatel the Get? Okay, so it's not even possible. That's what this
גמרא Gemara sounds like. אבל בקידושין
בריש האומר, aval be'Kiddushin berish ha'omer, אין שם כל זה האריכות. ein
sham kol zeh ha'arichus. You don't have this whole explanation. וכן בכל
הספרים, ve'chein be'chol ha'sefarim, and all it says over there in the
parallel סוגיא sugya is: נהי דבטליה לשליחותיה, nehi de'batlei li'shlichutei, it might
be he annulled the שליחות, shlichus, מידי דגיטא לא בטליה, midei de'gita
lo batlei, he did not annul it from a Get. So that's
just saying he didn't do it, it's not saying he's not able
to do it. Okay, that's in a parallel סוגיא. sugya. משמע, mashma,
it sounds from that סוגיא, sugya, דאי ביטלו בפירוש, de'ee bitlo be'perush,
if you explicitly did it, מודה רב נחמן דבטל. modeh Rav Nachman
de'batel. He agrees that it is. וכן צריך לומר, ve'chein tzarich lomar,
דגיטא לא חשיב מעשה כל זמן שלא הגיע ליד האשה. de'gita lo
chashiv ma'aseh kol zman she'lo higiah li'yad ha'isha.
And by the way, תוספות Tosafot says you actually necessarily have to
say that, that the Get is not yet a finished, done deal
that is irretractable as long as it hasn't gotten to the woman,
it's not yet irretractable and it could actually be annulled. Why do
you have to say that? דאי לאו הכי, de'ee lav hachi, תוספות
Tosafot says etc. etc. So תוספות Tosafot has some questions. Okay, but
what I wanted you to see is תוספות Tosafot raises a question:
bottom line, is the גמרא Gemara saying according to רב נחמן, Rav
Nachman, who it rules like, that it's impossible to change the status
of a Get, or is it just choosing to interpret that that's
what happened here? We're going to choose to interpret here that you
annulled the שליחות, shlichus, because it's still a little vague. I have
no idea why it's a little vague. Okay, but in theory, you
could actually annul it. So it's anyway, it's a little frustrating סוגיא.
sugya. There's this great למדות lamdus about the גט get as this
expression of the will of the husband and changing the status of
the גט, get, and in the end the גמרא Gemara sounds like,
yeah, all you really did was you you annulled the שליחות, shlichus,
meaning that if anyone's actually מבטל mevatel the גט get according to
what תוספות Tosafos is saying, רב נחמן Rav Nachman is saying, that
it could work...
it would be un... you cannot reuse it.
And then right, you cannot reuse it as opposed to מבטל mevatel
the status of the שליחות, shlichus, then it can just be reconstituted.
Right, exactly. Okay, so now let's move on. בראשונה היה עושה, barishona
haya oseh, originally, it was just at the bottom of the page,
originally he would make a בית דין beis din in his own
home town and then they said that won't work anymore. בפני כמה
הוא מבטלו? bifnei kama hu mevatlo? In this original status, okay, and
we'll see later why it will matter what was the case originally,
even though there was a תקנה takana to do away with this.
But originally, when he could make it in a בית דין, beis
din, not in front of the שליח, shaliach, not in front of
his wife, how many people would have to constitute the בית דין?
beis din? רב נחמן אמר בפני שנים, Rav Nachman amar bifnei shnayim,
we really not a normal בית דין, beis din, just two. רב
ששת אמר בפני גמל. Rav Sheshes amar bifnei gimel. No, a normal
בית דין, beis din, three. רב ששת אמר בפני גמל, בית דין
תני. Rav Sheshes amar bifnei gimel, beis din tani. It says a
בית דין. beis din. A בית דין beis din is three. רב
נחמן אמר בפני שנים, בי תרי נמי קרי להו... beih terei nami
kari lehu...
a בית דין. beis din. בי תרי נמי בית דין קרי להו.
beih terei nami beis din kari lehu. Two are also called a
בית דין. beis din. Now תוספות Tosafos because תוספות Tosafos feels that
since, well this is an interesting question, but I'll say two things.
First of all, תוספות Tosafos connects this to a position of רב
נחמן Rav Nachman in סנהדרין Sanhedrin that says actually two people שנים
שדנו דינם דין. shnayim shedanu dineihem din. That two people actually בדיעבד
bedieved count as a בית דין. beis din. Okay, so תוספות Tosafos
wonders is it limited to that? He says it's not limited to
that because other אמוראים Amoraim agree with רב נחמן Rav Nachman who
don't hold that position over there. Okay, so one is just to
say, no, he actually has a broader definition of what's a בית
דין. beis din. But the other approach is to say let's question
why you needed a בית דין. beis din. Why could we not
say originally that if the husband even did it in private, nobody
was around before רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel came with his תקנה, takana,
why didn't that annul the גט, get, right? Now maybe he couldn't
prove it, I don't know, okay, but those... but anyway, but that's
the question: why did he need a בית דין beis din originally?
Okay, so maybe the difference between saying two and three is exactly
that. The one who says two says, you know what, it's true.
Originally, all you needed was the husband's private expression that he is
annulling it. It was an expression of his will, he's retracting his
will. Or he made a שליח, shaliach, he retracts the שליחות. shlichus.
That all... the only thing you need is to prove that he
did it. You only need עדים. eidim. You don't fundamentally need a
בית דין. beis din. So even though it says בית דין, beis
din, it's really not about a בית דין. beis din. The other
approach would say, no no no, if especially if we think about
annulling the שליחות, shlichus, annulling the גט, get, the other approach says,
you know, since when, as the גמרא Gemara said before, since when
does a simple speech act have the weight of changing the status
of a גט get or whatever, you know, it needs to become
a judicial act. It needs to be like in the front of
בית דין, beis din, not just a private expression of will. Okay,
and therefore it really needs like a בית דין. beis din. Do
you have a question, Dena?
No, I just... I feel like that could fix some of our
contradictions earlier. Like if you said some of it was going by
one opinion and some of it was going by another, that like
if you need three... if you need a בית דין beis din
מבטל mevatel the גט, get, right? So when you don't have the
שליח, shaliach, I'm מבטל mevatel this... like it can only be talking
about the שליחות. shlichus. It can't be talking about the גט. get.
But if you were saying it's in front of a בית דין,
beis din, then you could actually be...
Right, it could be. Now I'm just seeing though that that nice
little סברא sevara למדות lamdus I gave doesn't... I think it doesn't
match up at all. Because before you also have רב נחמן Rav
Nachman and רב ששת, Rav Sheshes, and I think it reverses. Let
me see this. רב נחמן Rav Nachman said חוזר ומגרש בו, chozer
umegaresh bo,
which meant you're only מבטל mevatel the שליחות. shlichus. And רב נחמן
Rav Nachman here says, oh no, it does work. רב נחמן Rav
Nachman here says two. Oh, it's perfect. Look at that. Okay, I
thought I gave a שיעור shiur on this once before. Okay, so
it actually works out beautifully. רב נחמן Rav Nachman said you're only
being מבטל mevatel the שליחות shlichus the way the גמרא Gemara is
choosing to read it. So you can do that essentially privately. Maybe
you only need two witnesses to prove it happened. רב ששת Rav
Sheshes who is saying you're changing the status of the גט, get,
right? אינו חוזר ומגרש בו, eino chozer umegaresh bo, you have to
make that a judicial act, so you have to do it in
front of a בית דין beis din of three. Okay, but and
we will pick up tomorrow to see even though that's a nice
למדות lamdus and all of that, how can רב נחמן Rav Nachman
say that we call two people a בית דין? beis din? Normally
בית דין beis din always means three. He'll try to show places
where two actually is referred to as a בית דין. beis din.
See you.